Hello, and welcome back to
another episode with ItsDrDan.
And today we're going to be
learning about chemical bonding.
So what is chemical bonding?
What is it all about?
So this is an introductory video,
just going over the different
types of chemical bonds and how
exactly, how do we come across them?
How do we label them?
What do they look like?
So for this one, uh, what exactly a
bond is, is when two or more atoms
combine where they form a bond,
meaning that they have some type of
force of attraction between them.
Now, what is all the
driving force between these?
Why do they want to bond so badly?
Well, one of the things that you've
been learning about in your chemistry
course is that Most atoms, they do
not have a complete outer shell,
meaning that they aren't quite happy.
They want to have all
their electrons filled.
They don't want to react.
They want to be like a noble guest.
The goal is to be dignified,
just like a noble when they look
at these different elements.
So how can you do that?
Well, elements, they, what they're
going to do, they're going to combine.
Meaning that when this happens,
we will fill our valence level.
Remember, valence is your highest
quantum number, your outermost layer.
Think of an onion, it's
the outside of the onion.
So, now the goal is, is that you want
to have 8 electrons for these elements.
So, many of them want to have 8.
There are exceptions, which we'll
talk about in other videos, but
the goal is 8 for most of them.
Now, how can they do it though?
How can they get to 8?
Well, they can do all kinds of things.
How can you try to get, let's
say, if you want to think about
money, how can you get there?
Well, you could work for it, you
could borrow it, you could take
it, you could lose it, you could
do all kinds of things with it.
It's kind of the same idea with electrons.
So what can they do is they could give
their electrons away, meaning that that
will get them to an octet, possibly.
They could take electrons from other
Atoms and in the generally it's
like a bar like a bartering system.
They'll be happy as well.
So they don't mind losing them to write
give and take or we can share right now.
Each of these have their own benefits.
Different different types of atoms
will do all these different reactions.
So when we see this type of bonding
that's occurring, well, we represent
this either as compounds or as molecules.
So you're going to hear your
different professors and teachers
using these words a lot, and it's
going to get a little confusing.
Keep in mind they generally
mean a very similar definition,
but they do have a difference.
So compounds are whenever you have two
or more different types of atoms, meaning
like if you have a metal and a non-metal
or a metalloid and a non-metal maybe
are generally metals and non-metals.
So they're two different complete
different types of a of atoms.
Now, what that means is all
compounds are molecules here.
So molecules, if you notice, are
two or more atoms that are bonded.
It doesn't matter what they
are, as long as they're bonded.
So you could have a metal and a
metal, or a nonmetal and a nonmetal.
You can have a metal and a non
metal, as long as they are bonded.
So all compounds are molecules.
So you'll hear that word
kind of interchanged a lot.
Usually, we use compounds to
describe ionic species more often.
Now, we'll talk about this throughout
here, of course, in all these
videos, for you to understand that.
So what does that mean in the end
is not all molecules are compounds.
Remember, they have to be, in
order to be a compound, they
need to be two different types.
That's the most important
thing for this sentence.
Compounds, not all of them are
compounds, so compounds are
generally metals and nonmetals.
All right, let's take a further
look at these different,
so there are generally three types
of bonds that just as a general
classification for general chemistry,
the first, the three of them are
ionic, covalent, and metallic bonds.
We're going to talk briefly about
each one of them so you get a
basic idea of what they look like.
So ionic is when one atom donates
an electron and the other one
accepts, so it's that give and take.
Okay.
Now, when this happens, it's making an
electrostatic attraction, meaning it's
that positive and negative charge are
being attracted to each other, okay?
So positive and negative, right?
So this is where your predictable ions
are going to be very, very important.
This is when metals act
as what we call cations.
Remember, cats are positive.
Non-Metals Act as anions or as I
kind of sometimes say as onions.
Um, so anion and cat ions.
Now these can exist in
different subcategories.
They can be type one or type two.
Now, type one means that
the cat ion is predictable.
It's something that always has
the same charge no matter what.
So it's usually one of the
elements found in your first
two columns of your POC table.
or maybe ammonium as a polyatomic,
something that's always the same.
Type two is when you have a variable
charge, meaning that there is a
transition metal that's bonding.
Now, what do these guys look like?
Well, ionic compounds are always,
they exist as crystalline structures,
meaning that if you've ever looked
at, let's say you have table salt at
home, so you salt different food dishes
all the time, it's a crystal, right?
It looks like a little rock that
comes out of your container.
If you look at it under a really
powerful microscope, you actually
will see the crystal structure.
If you ever go to, geode exhibit, You'll
also see that all the different rocks
exist in crystalline structures as well.
This is because they are ionic
compounds that exist as a crystalline
lattice, meaning that they exist
in this repeating framework.
So you have Na plus as yellow orbs here,
and chlorine minus as green, and you
can see it's this alternating pattern.
Now, the thing about this though is,
we, it's very hard to count the number
of atoms and ions when you want to
illustrate these, so generally we like
to simplify these to the simplest ratio.
What we refer to this as is a
formula unit, okay, so that's
the important word here.
So now the good news is, this
formula unit is all based on your
predictable, all based on your charges.
So, for example, if I have, let's
say, Na and Cl here, remember
from before, the goal was 8, so
how do we get to 8 electrons?
Well, what can happen is, remember,
it's all about giving and taking.
So sodium has a, wants to give
away its one electron here.
So what will it become if it does that?
Well, then we'll have Na plus, right?
And if you remember from your predictable
charges in the periodic table, that's
exactly where that charge comes from.
And then chlorine on the other
side will now have a complete
Um, eight electrons as a result.
So we can now fill in that
extra electron from sodium.
And then we would write that in
brackets with a negative charge to
say, like, hey, this guy does have
its complete negative, uh, charge.
Sometimes this can also be
written where the negative is
inside the brackets as well.
It generally depends on this notation.
But this is a general notation where
we use brackets to show that ion.
So keep that in mind.
I will put that this
is a general notation.
Um, so we're all about trying to give and
take these different types of electrons as
we are looking at these different species.
Now, overall, when we write the final
name for this, we would just write NaCl.
And if you'd like to, you could label this
as an ionic type one compound, and it's
also considered a binary ionic compound.
Binary, meaning that there's two.
So where do I get two from?
There's an NA and a cl.
It's two.
So type one is that they're
predictable, being that they have
A plus as a NA has a plus charge,
and it always has a plus charge.
So that's the general idea for Ionic.
Let's look at an example.
I have an ionic compound here,
which is a metal plus a non metal.
So we have calcium, which is our
metal, and fluorine, our non metal.
So calcium, which is going to be our
cat ion here, is going to be likely to
give away its electrons to get eight.
So when it gives away its electrons,
it will give one away to each fluorine,
and as a result, we will have calcium 2
Okay, now what about all the fluorines?
So what we're gonna do is we're gonna
put the fluorines on each side here.
And we're now going to draw in all
the different electrons, so let's
draw the ones that calcium gave first.
And then we'll put the other
eight dots around this.
And now we can see that we have
a complete octet around fluorine.
which makes it very, very happy.
And then we also have a complete
octet around calcium as well.
Keep in mind that calcium does
have a complete octet because it
loses its outer shell electrons,
just as a kind of quick reminder.
So it loses its 4s2 electrons and it
will have a final configuration Um, where
essentially it will be equivalent to
argon or its electron configuration for
those of you who are learning about that.
So its final valence level will
now be 3s2 3p6 and you can write
that it has a neon over here.
So, which is argon.
Okay.
So it also has those
eight valence electrons.
Let's take a look at covalent.
bonding to learn about the next time.
So covalent bonding is all
about sharing of electrons.
Meaning we try to make this as
equal of a partnership as possible.
Now keep in mind, sometimes this
is not always the most equal.
You generally can also have a little
bit, maybe it lean one way or the other.
But let's just for now, keep it simple.
It's about equal.
So the way that this works instead is that
each one of these will kind of come in.
So I'll bring a hydrogen on each side.
And we literally share our electrons.
So, as a result, hydrogen has a complete
external layer, and so does oxygen.
They equally share all those
electrons that are around it.
So we kind of can notice oxygen has
1,2,3,4,5, 6, 7, 8, and hydrogen
is one of those exceptions where
it can only actually have only
two, so everything is happy.
So generally the way that we will kind
of illustrate this as a happy bond,
um, for covalent is we'll draw a line
to illustrate that we have a bond.
So if we move all these different
species, we'll get rid of these
electrons here, and we will write a
line to represent a chemical bond.
So this is a covalent bond.
This represents that two electrons
are being shared amongst that bond.
So now what species participate
in this is generally anything
referred to as molecular.
So, or like a molecule, um, also
binary acids and oxyacids as
well fall under covalent as well.
But the main one here is anything
that's molecular, is what you are
looking for, for labeling these.
We refer to covalent generally
as molecules, whereas ionic
is generally molecules.
You're cut your compounds being
at these are the hydrogen oxygen
are both nonmetals, right?
They're the same type.
Let's look at the last one So metallic
bonds, which generally does not come up
a lot in like introductory chemistry or?
Sometimes it comes up maybe by general
chemistry too, you'll see metallic
bonds when you're learning about like
maybe coordinate chemistry, um, but it's
something that doesn't get talked about a
lot unless you're taking a lot of physics
or engineering, maybe some very heavy
duty bonding courses or in if you're
trying to learn about semiconductors.
So, what it is, is atoms that are
connected via a sea of electrons,
meaning that this is between metals only.
So what do I mean by
that sea of electrons?
Well, I have a, let's say I
have this, um, this water bucket
here and it's made of iron.
Well, all the iron that's in this,
each one, all the different atoms that
are in it are giving off electrons.
They willingly are giving them away.
So because of that, it's causing
all of them to have a very, very
strong bond amongst themselves.
So this is just more of a demonstration
to see kind of what this is like,
where there's all kinds of wild physics
phenomenon that can happen because of this
sea of electrons, um, with different types
of, different unit, quantum type units.
But just keep in mind metallic bonds occur
between metals, and that's all we need
to know for this, uh, for this video.
Okay, so this was the three
different types of bonding.
I hope this video helped.
Please feel free to, please watch my
follow up video on how to interpret
a chemical bond or a chemical
formula so you know how to read them.
Um, there will be more videos
to come soon, and thank you
all so much for listening.
I hope you have a wonderful day.
And please hit that like and
subscribe button if you haven't,
and I will see you all later.
Bye now!